Welcome back.
Meetings can be an effective method to
distribute information, communicate with
your team and stakeholders, and
help keep a project on track.
In this video,
you'll learn how to organize and
facilitate effective team meetings that
will lead to a successful project.
While the size, purpose, and
format of meetings may differ,
effective meetings always have
the following elements in common.
They're structured, intentional,
collaborative, and inclusive.
Let's study these elements in more detail.
First, effective meetings are structured.
This means they start and end on time.
The attendees have been
carefully selected.
The meeting topics are prioritized.
And the designated note
taker has been assigned.
Managing the meeting time and
audience lets participants know that
they're valued and appreciated.
Remember that everyone's time is valuable.
If someone's presence is unnecessary, you
don't need to invite them to the meeting.
Maybe you can share the notes.
Include people who can
contribute to the discussion and
anyone who will be directly
affected by the topics discussed.
Structured meetings also have
an agenda with prioritized topics.
So the most important items
are given appropriate attention.
It's good to think about and
set expectations for
how long you expect the group
to spend on a given topic.
This is defined as timeboxing, which just
means you're setting a time limit for
discussion.
In a timebox, you give each topic a buffer
of a few minutes to make sure you're not
over packing your agenda.
Keep the meeting time in mind and
make sure you schedule enough time for
the topic you need to cover.
If there are several topics you need to
address consider scheduling a few shorter
meetings with just one or
two topics as their focus.
After your first few team meetings, think
about the pacing to know if you need to
be more generous with the time
given to each topic or
if the group has time for a little more.
If you get through your topics
before your time is up,
don't be afraid to call a meeting early.
Everybody loves having their time back.
Finally, a structured meeting should
have a designated note taker.
So you or anyone else can refer
to the meeting notes later and
find out what was discussed.
The note taker could be you or
another meeting attendee.
For this reason be clear about how,
when, and
to whom the meetings outcomes are shared.
Again, this all depends on the type
of meeting you're having and
who is attending.
I'll loop back to describe some
different types of project meetings in
the next video.
The next point to consider is that
effective meetings are also intentional.
This means they have a clearly
stated purpose and expectations,
which should be in the meeting agenda
as well as the meeting invite.
So everyone understands
why they're attending.
The agenda needs to set
clear expectations for
what needs to occur before and
during the meeting.
It helps attendees prepare, keeps
everyone focused on the right topics, and
clarifies meeting expectations and goals.
The purpose of your meeting might be to
make a decision, assign tasks, propose/
invent an idea, or something else.
Your meeting's purpose, or goal,
describes the reason you're meeting and
what you'd like to achieve.
A well designed agenda increases the
group's ability to address problems and
prevents wasting time.
For example, you may be reviewing
last month's business sales and
setting goals for the next month.
Maybe your group needs to choose
coordinators for an upcoming event.
Or your goal could be to have your
supervisor prioritize a list of tasks.
The purpose might change from meeting
to meeting, or it could stay the same.
If input is needed by attendees, be sure
to send any pre-reading materials in
advance of the meeting so that everyone
shows up prepared to participate.
Depending on the purpose meetings
can be formal or informal,
have as few as two or three group
members or have hundreds of attendees.
Whatever it is, make sure you state
a clear thoughtful purpose and
strive to achieve that purpose
by the end of the allotted time.
Another element of effective meetings is
encouraging a collaborative environment.
Collaboration is when people work
together to produce or create something.
There are lots of ways to make
your meetings collaborative,
even if the purpose is for
one person to share important
information with the rest of the group.
One easy way to do this
is to be sure the agenda
isn’t just full of presentations
where participants are talked at.
Be sure the agenda is clear about
the objectives of the session.
Will a decision be made, or is the session
for information and discussion?
Second, have a digital shared meeting
document and encourage participants to
write any comments or
thoughts directly in the document.
But more importantly,
remind them that the notes will be shared.
This encourages active listening and
participation in real
time during the meeting.
Last, it's important to respect and
embrace each individual's preferred
communication style even in meetings,
especially in collaborative meetings.
Let folks know they're welcome to
respond verbally, through the chat,
in the meeting notes, or
in any other format you'd like to include.
The final element of an effective
meeting is that it's inclusive.
Inclusivity is the practice or
policy of including people who might
otherwise be excluded or marginalized.
When it's done well, inclusion
leads to excellent collaboration,
ensuring that every participants
contributions are valued.
As a project manager, you play a critical
role in ensuring that meeting attendees
feel supported and included.
So offering additional resources for
ways to participate is helpful.
For both in-person and virtual meetings,
consider appointing a meeting moderator or
facilitator.
This person will guide the meeting and
help participants ask questions in
real-time, while someone
else is presenting.
This way the presenter can stay focused
on their topic while the moderator pays
attention to the participants and
can help guide participants
on when they can chime in.
It's also a good idea to leave
space in the meeting for
participants who've been quiet.
At the close of a topic or
before the meeting ends,
you might consider going around
the room once in a while and
asking each person to comment on
a particular issue or question.
I like to call this a final flight
check before everyone takes off and
goes their separate ways.
A key component of inclusivity is
ensuring that your meetings and
presentations are accessible.
You'll find more information on
this in the course resources.
Another thing to consider is the level of
internet access when conducting virtual
meetings.
For those without strong internet access,
provide a phone dialing option.
Most online meeting tools, including
Google Meet and Zoom, have this option.
Let participants know it's okay to
turn off their cameras if they need to
improve the connection or
adjust the video quality.
Focusing on inclusion helps
build a sense of belonging and
serves as a reminder that we live in a
world with many different kinds of people.
Creating a meeting space where people
have different views, backgrounds, and
experiences can do their best work and
be there for one another is key.
These tips aren't exhaustive by any means,
but hopefully they can be useful to
start empowering others to
meaningfully join in and contribute.
When done right, meetings can be
incredibly useful communication tools.
That's why it's important to be
purposeful when designing meetings
that are structured, intentional,
collaborative, and inclusive.
This will earn you a reputation for
writing efficient, inclusive,
successful meetings where everyone
feels appreciated, which is great for
your project and your career.
Great job, so
now we know a bit more about the effective
methods to distribute information,
communicate with your team and
stakeholders, and keep a project on track.
We've also learned some of the elements
of creating an effective meeting like
including a clear agenda, attendee list,
taking detailed notes, and more.
In the next video, we'll learn all about
the most common types of project meetings.